<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Konstantinos Loupasakis</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Konstantinos Loupasakis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 15:30:24 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to efficiently trigger file downloads in PHP</title>
      <link>/posts/efficient_downloads_in_php/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 15:30:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/efficient_downloads_in_php/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making a download happen in PHP is dead simple: Just set your Content-Type and send it&amp;rsquo;s contents to the client through the standard output, usually with the use of &lt;code&gt;echo&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what you want to avoid when you try doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how I used to do it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;header(&#39;Content-Type: application/octet-stream&#39;);
header(&#39;Content-Transfer-Encoding: Binary&#39;);
header(&#39;Content-disposition: attachment; filename=&amp;quot;&#39; . basename($file_location) . &#39;&amp;quot;&#39;);
echo file_get_contents($file_location);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This might work fine for small files but there is a caveat: It will load the entire file to memory, which sooner or later will bring your server to it&amp;rsquo;s knees.&lt;br&gt;
Here is a more memory-efficient way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;header(&#39;Content-Type: application/octet-stream&#39;);
header(&#39;Content-Transfer-Encoding: Binary&#39;);
header(&#39;Content-disposition: attachment; filename=&amp;quot;&#39; . basename($file_location) . &#39;&amp;quot;&#39;);
readfile($file_location);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The difference between the two snippets is a subtle, but important one: &lt;code&gt;file_get_contents&lt;/code&gt; returns all the contents of the file into a single string. Which, in turn, means that if our file is, say 1GB, we have used 1GB of our server RAM just so that we can echo our file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;readfile&lt;/code&gt; on the other hand echoes the files, without having to load the entire thing in memory; it internally goes through the file and echoes it’s contents with minimal memory footprint.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First</title>
      <link>/posts/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 12:27:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/first/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time there was a little blog.&lt;br&gt;
Full of potential.&lt;br&gt;
Empty of words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a forgotten draft. This is a reminder, a ghost of the days of procratination.&lt;br&gt;
If you read this it can mean two things. Either I never bother adding enough words in the word-machine, or you are a dedicaded reader, a blog archaiologist digging through the archives for long forgotten knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope the easter egg you found was worth it 😊&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>